Hello, welcome back to our course today we are going to talk about lists
and matrices. Alright, so lists in R can contain
all sorts of components, for example numeric values, character vectors, lists, etc.
And these components of our list can have names. For example
the first list here has two elements. It's of length two, actually.
The first component is this vector, numeric vector, and the second component is the string "Hallo".
Now, I defined a similar list. And here, our components are with names, so now I call the first component numeric
and the second component character. How can I access
the elements of the list? Well, I could use this double bracket, or a single bracket
and dollar sign. How do they work? Imagine now that we have a family list
with three elements. The first element is father, the second is mother, and the third is called
n.children. If I would like to access the first element,
either I can call it by its name, so then I could use the dollar sign:
family$father, and then I have exactly: the first element is Joseph.
Or, I could just write the number of that element, so the index of that element. So basically,
family[[1]], and I get the same: Joseph. Now, if I use a single bracket,
what do I obtain? I obtain a sublist. So, now imagine that I would like to see
the second and the third component of that list.
What do I get here? I get a sublist with two elements, mother and n.children.
What happens now if I use unlist function for a list?
First, let us define this new object, A. And I apply unlist to a family.
And now, if I look at how A looks like, I can see a vector.
I can see a vector with 3 elements, Joseph, Annie, 2.
And elements of this vector have names: Father, mother, and children.
If I check a class of a family, this is a list, of course, because as you might remember, we define it as a list.
If I check the length of a family, it's 3, because we had 3 elements.
Now, if I compare it to a class of A,
then, this is character, because all the elements from that list
where coerced to a character. And then, if I check the length of A, it's 3, because this is a vector with 3
elements. Alright, so now let us talk about matrices. So, matrix can be constructed using the matrix function here in R.
And now, how does it work? So here, I have A,
which is now this matrix, and then with elements from 1 to 16.
And I would like to have it 4 rows. Now we could see that these elements are indeed here,
but all these elements are listed first, within the first column, so 1, 2, 3, 4, then within the second column, 5, 6, 7, 8, etc.
If we would like to have elements listed by rows, then we need to
define this third parameter here, byrow = TRUE.
And now we can see that element runs by rows. So we have 1, 2, 3, 4
in the first row, 5, 6, 7, 8 in the second row, etc.
We could also construct matrices from vectors using functions cbind() and rbind().
So basically, what do they do? If I use a cbind(), it binds vectors by column,
and if I do rbind(), it binds vectors
by row. Here, I would like to construct two vectors.
I would like to have vectors with random variables, and this time
from binomial distribution, so you might remember that, to define the random variable
from a binomial distribution, I need to have a size,
here, this n is called size, and we have 5. And the probability of success.
Probability of success is 0.6 in the first case, and the probability of success is 0.1 in the second case, and I would like to have four elements.
Now, if I apply a function bind to X and Y, what do I have?
These two vectors are bound by rows. So the first row
and the second row. And then, in the second case, we have these two vectors
bound by column. So the first column is a vector X, and the second column is a vector Y.
How can we access
matrix elements? Well, once again, we can do it through brackets.
And basically, if I apply bracketing to A, and then, for example, I ask
for Ith and Jth element, it means that I'm asking for an element in row I and column J
over matrix A. And here, row and column indexing starts at 1.
And the same principle applies for rows and columns as for vectors. For example, here
I define a matrix, A, with elements from 1 to 12,
and I would like it to have 3 rows and 4 columns.
So I can see, once again, here, the elements run
first, within the first column, then, within the second column, etc.
Now, I would like to access elements in the first and second row,
and the third column. So, first, second row,
and then third column. I have 7, 8. Now, I would like to access elements in minus one row.
What does it mean? It means that my matrix has 3 rows, 1, 2, 3, and minus 1 means that I'm accessing elements
in the second row, so here. And then, in the first column, it's
2. And I have 3. So, from minus 1
to the end. And, in the third example, what do we have? We have the first
row, and then we would like to have the first and the fourth column.
So, the first row, and then the first, and the fourth
column. And then we end up with elements 1 and 10.
Alright, so there are a few useful functions to get the dimension of X, so here you can see that my matrix
X, once again, it has 10 elements. Which run from 1 to 10.
I have 2 rows and 5 columns. And if I ask for the dimension of X, it's 2 and 5. Why? Because I have
2 rows and 5 columns. If I ask for
the number of rows, so nrow, this is 2.
If I ask for the number of columns, I have 5, because I have 5 columns.
What does length give me? Length gives me the total number of elements, so 2 times 5:
The number of rows times the number of columns, and this is 10.
Alright. We could also give names to rows and columns.
Once these names are given, we could access the elements
through the names of the rows and columns. So, for example, here, I'm defining this
Matrix B with 4 elements and the number of rows is 2.
And I'm giving the names to first, rows. My rows are called A and B, and second, I'm giving, names to colums
A and B. So now, if I access the element in the row A, and in the column
A, I'm accessing the first element, so 1. Now, if I redefine only columns,
I could do it through colnames. And then I'm redefining the names of the columns in this matrix, and I'm giving it names B, A.
I could also redefine only names of rows. And these are redefined through applying this function rownames, B and A.
And now, if I look into the output
of this matrix B, then
I have here two rows, B, A, two columns B, A,
and all the elements of my matrix. And now, if I would like to access element
AA, it refers now to the second row and the second column, so my element is 4.
Alright, let me briefly talk about constructing matrices from
vectors. A vector can be transformed to a matrix by changing its dimension.
For example, here, I have a vector X, 4, 2, 3, 2, and then I would like to transform it
to a matrix. How do I do it? I just write dim(x), and then I write how many rows and how many columns
this matrix should have. So this matrix, new matrix, so basically I transform that factor X to now
a matrix X with 2 rows, 1, 2. And two columns 1, 2.
Now let us talk about sums and products. If we have a matrix X
with 20 elements, 4 rows and 5 columns,
and we apply a sum function to X, I get to the sum of all elements.
Similarly, if I apply prod function to X. I get a result of a product of all elements.
If I apply colSums, then I get a sum
over the elements in each column. So what do we have here?
We have 10, 26, 42, 58, 74, so we have 5 sums, because we had 5 columns.
Similarly, if I apply rowSums, then I can get the sums over the elements
in each row. So, we had 4 rows, and we have
four sums. If I apply a function colMeans,
then I get the means over the elements in each column, so I had 5 columns,
now, I get 5 means, because I took an average of elements in each column.
Similarly, if I apply a function row means. What do I get? I get means of elements in each row, I had 4 rows,
I get 4 means. Alright, and then let us,
also talk about cumulative functions on vectors and matrices. So now imagine that I have this vector A,
and, I would like to now apply this function cumsum(). Basically, what does it give me? It gives me a cumulative sum.
The first element was just the first element, I'm not adding any other elements, because I have only
just this first element. Now, if I add
the second element to the first element, I get 3. If I add the third element to
this second element of this vector, I get 6.
Now, if I add 4, so 4th element to this element of a new vector, I get 10, etc. So it's a cumulative sum,
it cumulates this summation over different elements. Similarly, cumprod():
We multiply elements. In the first case, we have only one element, so it's 1.
Then I multiply 1 times 2, this is 2, then I multiply this 2 times 3, this is 6.
I multiply 6 by 4, this is 24, etc. Now, if I
define another vector, B, and I would like to apply this function cummin(),
then, what do we get? We get a cumulative minimum, so once again, in case of the first element, I had only one element, so the minimum of one element
is just this element. Then, a minimum of
two first elements is 2. A minimum of
this 2 and 1 is 1, and etc. So a minimum of this 1, and
the fourth element from the original vector is, once again, 1, etc.
Similarly, for cummax(), so here we have the maximum of one value is 3,
maximum of this 3, and the second value, it's 3. Maximum of this second value and the third value from the original value is 3,
until we hit 4 here, because we always had 3. So the maximum of 3 and this
4 here would be, finally, 4. So for this reason, we had
4 until the end of this cummax(),
aplication on the vector B. Okay so let me stop here, and then in the next video
we are going to talk about special matrices. And a little bit about arrays.